A Guide to the Harry W. Sanders Papers, 1913-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Harry W. Sanders Papers, 1913-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-002
1.2 cu. ft. 3 boxes
Papers of Harry W. Sanders, graduate of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (BS, 1916); professor of agricultural education and vocational education (1925-1963) and professor emeritus of vocational education (1963-1985) at Virginia Tech; vocational teacher-trainer in Puerto Rico (1932-1933); co-founder of Future Farmers of Virginia (basis of Future Farmers of America). Includes correspondence, articles, printed materials, awards, scrapbooks, and photographs relating to Sanders' personal life and professional career (including his year in Puerto Rico, developing a vocational agricultural education program), as well as the histories of Virginia Tech and Blacksburg, Virginia.
Sanders, Harry W. (Harry Warinner), 1895-1984
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Harry W. Sanders Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1975. An addition to the collection, consisting of three scrapbooks, was donated in 1995.
Biographical Note
Harry Warinner Sanders, the son of William C. and Rosa Gary Sanders, was born in Dumbarton, Virginia on August 29, 1895. After graduating from Virginia Polytechnic Institute with a BS in agriculture (1916), Sanders worked as a teacher of vocational agriculture in Manassas, Virginia from 1917 to 1924, then as a district supervisor of vocational agriculture in northern Virginia from 1924 to 1925, when he was hired by VPI as an assistant professor of agricultural education. He married Julia Ayres Maloney (1896-1993) on August 31, 1921.
At a VPI on-campus conference in 1925, Sanders was one of the co-founders of a statewide program for high school vocational education, to be known as the Future Farmers of Virginia, which would eventually form the basis for a national organization, the Future Farmers of America. In 1927, Sanders received his MS from VPI and was named an associate professor of agricultural education that same year. From 1932 to 1933, Sanders was on leave in Puerto Rico, developing a vocational agricultural education program there. Beginning in 1934, Sanders played an important role in the expansion of VPI's Department of Agricultural Education, renamed the Department of Vocational Education. In 1940, Sanders was named professor of vocational education, and he served as department head from 1956 until his retirement in 1962. In 1963, he was named professor emeritus of vocational education. He was a member of Phi Kappa Phi, Omicron Delta Kappa, Alpha Zeta, the American Vocational Association, the Virginia Education Association, the Virginia Academy of Science, and the American Red Cross. Harry W. Sanders died on January 17, 1984, and was buried in Westview Cemetery, Blacksburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Harry W. Sanders, graduate of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (BS, 1916); professor of agricultural education and vocational education (1925-1963) and professor emeritus of vocational education (1963-1985) at Virginia Tech; vocational teacher-trainer in Puerto Rico (1932-1933); and co-founder of the Future Farmers of Virginia (basis of the Future Farmers of America). The collection contains such materials as correspondence; awards; articles; printed materials; scrapbooks; and photographs relating to Sanders' personal life and professional career, as well as the histories of Virginia Tech and Blacksburg, Virginia.
The bulk of the collection focuses on Sanders' interest in vocational education and his tenure at Virginia Tech through correspondence, memoranda, instructional materials, and reports. The collection also contains a folder relating to Sanders' civic activities, particularly his work with the local YMCA and the American Red Cross. Also included are more than 100 typescript articles written by Sanders, used either in publications or as the basis for talks. The year that Sanders spent establishing a program of vocational education in Puerto Rico is represented in several issues of the Puerto Rican "Vocational Education in Agriculture" newsletter; a subject folder containing correspondence, reports, and printed material; a photo album; and a scrapbook. The collection contains several other scrapbooks, as well: one devoted to vocational education; one to the history of Virginia Tech, especially prominent personalities in the university's development; and two on topics relating to the history of Blacksburg, Virginia, including organizations, churches, historic sites, and prominent community members. The scrapbooks on Virginia Tech and Blacksburg consist largely of newspaper clippings. A small collection of photographs completes the collection and contains several images of Virginia Tech campus groups, including the "Ragged Rangers" (1913), the Corps of Cadets in formation (1915/1916), and the 1914/1915 junior class.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by item type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection to be added to the Rare Book Collection:
The Virginia Agricultural Instructor, Jun 15 1921; Aug 15 1921; Dec 15 1921 (LD5655 A631 A359 VPI Spec)
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Faculty; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Virginia Tech correspondence and memoranda, 1925-1975 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Vocational education, 1932-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
- General education, 1940-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Civic activities, 1939-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Articles, 1942-1966 (Box-folder 1-5-10)
- "Vocational Education in Agriculture," 1932-1933 (Box-folder 1-11-12)
- Puerto Rico, 1932-1933, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Puerto Rico photo album, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Puerto Rico scrapbook, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Vocational education scrapbook, ca. 1919-1975 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Virginia Tech scrapbook, 1931-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 3-1)
- Blacksburg scrapbook, 1961-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 3-2)
- Blacksburg scrapbook, 1928-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 3-3)
- Photographs, 1913-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)